let's look now at direct memory access so
we have discussed interrupts and now we know
that the CPU can be working on something and let
the controller of a device send the signal when
something happens like some output has been
written disk or some input is available
for the CPU and so on
so there is an extra mechanism that also is
supported hardware that takes away
even more job from the CPU when it comes to
transferring large amounts of data to specific
devices and that is direct memory access
the idea is that if you have to transfer a big
chunk of data from main memory to the disk
for example since you have to send them in
specific chunks depending on what is the size
of the buffers you have at the controller
and the device to transfer data
having the CPU do this job would even if it
is optimized with interrupts it would still
consume time that the CPU can actually spend
running other processes
so what happens in modern hardware is that you
have a dedicated controller that is the dma
controller the direct memory access that
you can just think of as
an extra controller that takes care of transferring
stuff/data from memory to devices or
from devices to memory and then notify the
CPU when the transfer is complete so it's an
extra helper if you want at the hardware level
that takes care of transferring data from
the main memory to the devices in both directions
depending of
course on the type of device so basically
when you initiate when you want to initiate
the transfer of using direct memory access
the host writes in a specific portion or address
in memory that the DMA has access specifying
basically what information needs to be copied
and what is the destination and then the
controller of the DMA takes care
of actually doing the copy /
the transferring of data
you need of course an handshaking protocol
routine also when you want to coordinate with
the DMA this is about of course
the controllers that need to transfer data
using that the DMA controller for example
a disk that wants to
use the DMA controller and also in this case you
have dedicated lines for requests and acknowledgment
from the DMA controller so I
think the easiest is if I show you this image
here so let's say the CPU is running
a certain process and then at a certain point
it needs to transfer data
to the disk a big chunk of data to the disk so
this is step one what is happening in your
computer modern hardware is that
the CPU will send the request to the controller
to transfer the desired amount of data from
a disk to main memory
after that the controller of the disk will
actually coordinate with the DMA controller
the direct memory access controller here
and send the data to disk controller so basically
the DMA is now acting instead of the
CPU when it comes to taking the data that
comes from the disk and placedthat into memory
at a
specific buffer so the DMA takes care of
this work while the CPU is able to do other
things run other processes it will take
a while for the disk for the controller of
the disk to send the bytes to the DMA controller
and the controller will keep adding to the
buffer here in the main memory until of course
everything has been written to memory then
the interrupt that is sent to the CPU to say
the data you wanted from the disk is now
in memory will be actually generated by the
DMA controller
so the CPU reaches the point in a process
in which a system call says you need to transfer
something from the disk then the controller
of the disk communicates with the DMA so the
CPU goes on doing other things
and the final interrupt that will create a
context switch eventually so that the CPU can
go and start running again the process that
was waiting for the data comes from the DMA
controller in this case